Guide to the Lorin Edgar Kerr Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lorin Edgar Kerr papers
1941-1981
MS 785
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
20.25
The papers consist of correspondence, statistical reports, and organization files, writings and printed matter, which document Lorin Kerr's work in the United Mine Workers Department of Occupational Health. Kerr's active participation in professional organizations, such as the American Public Health Association, District of Columbia Public Health Organization, and the Group Health Association of America, and his term as visiting professor at Howard University are also documented in the papers. The papers relating to the American Public Health Association, where Kerr served as president (1974) and executive board member are particularly voluminous and include correspondence, minutes, memoranda and clippings on occupational and environmental issues. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Kerr, Lorin E., 1909-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lorin E. Kerr, 1977-1980, and of Alan Derickson, 1998.
Scope and Contents
The Kerr Papers consist of twenty linear feet of correspondence, statistical reports, organization files, and reprints and other writings, organized in four series: UNITED MINE WORKERS OF AMERICA, OTHER PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES, WRITINGS, and PERSONAL PAPERS. Approximately one third of the papers concern the U. M.W.A. Department of Occupational Health and date from 1967 to 1978. The remainder of the papers extends from 1948 to 1978, with a few items dating from 1943 to 1948.
Series I, UNITED MINE WORKERS OF AMERICA, is organized in two sections, Correspondence and Subject Files and Welfare and Retirement Fund. The first section consists of Kerr's office correspondence as director of the Department of Occupational Health. Most of the section is arranged alphabetically by name or subject; the interoffice correspondence is placed at the end of the section and is arranged chronologically.
The bulk of the correspondence extends from the establishment of the Department of Occupational Health in June 1969 through 1978, although a few letters date from 1967 and 1968. The alphabetical correspondence includes exchanges with associates in public health and other fields, elected officials, miners and their families, and professional and labor organizations. Also included is extensive correspondence with the United States Departments of Labor and of Health, Education, and Welfare (D.H.E.W.). The D.H.E.W. files contain a large amount of general correspondence covering health legislation, social security, and health-related conferences; the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health folder (158) contains material of special value regarding health standards. The alphabetical files include some correspondence with colleagues in the union and in the Department of Occupational Health; there are cross references to the material in the more voluminous chronological interoffice correspondence files.
For the most part the interoffice correspondence files contain material relating to the daily operation of the department, including circulated memoranda, press releases, and pamphlets regarding facilities. personnel, and equipment. The files do include some items of interest, however. A variety of letters and other materials concerning the Medical Advisory Committee of the Department of Occupational Health reflects the various issues which concerned the department in its early days. Also, the Interoffice Files occasionally focuses on such subjects as the Federal Coal Mine Health and Safety Act of 1969 (1970 Jan 14, Mar 24), on health and safety disputes arising in the mines (1974 Jul 19), and on issues surrounding the operation of the union's hospitals and clinics (1970 Mar 4, 1973 Feb 13, 1975 Nov 11). The files also include occasional letters with U.M.W.A. presidents William A. (Tony) Boyle, and Arnold Miller.
The Welfare and Retirement Fund section is made up of a variety of statistical reports for the fund dating from 1948 to 1968, including an extensive run of Medical Care Statistics (1952-1958).
Series II, OTHER PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES, contains files from Kerr's participation in professional organizations and as a visiting professor at Howard University. The series dates from 1944 to 1977 and is organized in six sections: American Public Health Association, District of Columbia Department of Public Health, Public Health Council, District of Columbia Public Health Association, Group Health Association of America, Howard University, and National Institutes on Rehabilitation and Health Services.
The American Public Health Association section is the largest in the series and is divided into General Papers and Committees and Sections. The General Papers are most extensive for the 1970's, when Kerr served as president (1974) and executive board member; they include correspondence, minutes, and other material. Much of the correspondence covers routine administrative matters, but some letters concern Kerr's efforts to promote stronger positions on radiation hazards, occupational respiratory diseases, air pollution, health regulations for farm workers, and other occupational and environmental issues.
The District of Columbia Department of Public Health, Public Health Advisory Council section contains the files kept by Kerr during his tenure as chairman of the Council (1966-1968). In addition to general correspondence, minutes, and committee files, the section's "historical" file on the implementation of Medicaid in the District contains correspondence, bills, newsclippings, and statements by Kerr.
The Group Health Association of America section extends from 1952 to 1968 and is of special interest. Kerr was an officer and active member of the American Labor Health Association from 1952 forward. The Background Material subsection contains information on the A.L.H.A. and on its merger with the Group Health Federation of America in May 1959, which created the G.H.A.A.. The General Papers contain correspondence, and minutes from Kerr's appointment as a member of the board of directors and executive board and from his term as president (1966-1968). They also include subject correspondence regarding legislation and other issues. The Conferences subsection contains an extensive run of Proceedings of the Group Health Institute.
Series III, WRITINGS, is arranged chronologically (1943-1978), and is made up of reprints, United Mine Workers Journal columns, texts of speeches and Congressional testimony, and other writings by Kerr. The files also include some related correspondence and reference material. The texts of Kerr's testimony before Congressional committees are of special interest. In addition to frequent statements regarding black lung disease the texts cover a variety of topics, including national health insurance, the budgets for the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare and the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health, and health standards.
Series IV, PERSONAL PAPERS, consists of a few folders of correspondence, most concerning personal financial matters, and newsclippings regarding Kerr's activities and appointments. It also includes one folder of biographical information and photographs of Kerr's wife, Goldie Krantz.
The Kerr Papers were donated to Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, by Dr. Kerr in two accessions, one in 1977 and the other in 1980. The papers are part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection, which also includes the papers of Kerr's wife, Goldie Krantz (Ms. Group 780), and of several of his associates in medical care and health policy.
Biographical / Historical
Lorin Edgar Kerr has been a leader in the field of occupational health for more than four decades. Born in Toledo, Ohio, in 1909, he was educated at the University of Toledo (B.A., 1931) and the University of Michigan (M.D., 1935; M.S.P.H., 1939). From 1937 to 1944 he served in a number of municipal and county public health departments in Ohio and Michigan. Kerr joined the United States Public Health Service in 1944, first in the War Food Administration and later in the Industrial Hygiene Division. While with the Industrial Hygiene Division he provided consultant services for labor unions which were then beginning to develop their own medical care programs.
In October 1948 Kerr joined the newly formed Welfare and Retirement Fund of the United Mine Workers of America, accepting an appointment as an area medical administrator in Morgantown, West Virginia. From 1951 to 1969 he served as assistant to the medical director of the Welfare and Retirement Fund. While with the fund Kerr developed the U.M.W.A. Department of Occupational Health, the first occupational medical program to be established by a major labor union. He was appointed as the first director of the department in 1969, a position he has continued to hold.
Kerr's work with the United Mine Workers had an important impact on legislation and on the medical and public health professions, and it has contributed to a national awareness of the significance of environmental and occupational health standards. Occupational dust disease, especially coal workers' pneumonoconiosis (black lung), was one of Kerr's major concerns from the beginning of his employment with the Welfare and Retirement Fund, and it became his primary responsibility after his appointment as director of the Department of Occupational Health. He recognized that respiratory impairment in coal miners is attributable to coal dust, even though black lung, unlike other diseases, is not always verifiable through pathological tests. By seeking recognition of, and compensation for, black lung disease he was responsible for helping to create a much broader definition of the relationship between occupation and disease. Largely through Kerr's efforts black lung became recognized as a disease entity, and he played an active role in the passage of the Coal Mine Health and Safety Act of 1969 and its amendment in 1972. The 1969 act created a black lung compensation program for coal miners, and the 1972 amendment extended benefits to all miners with fifteen or more years of service who suffered respiratory impairment, whether or not pneumonoconiosis was pathologically verifiable.
In addition to his service with the United Mine Workers, Kerr advocated and supported the development of occupational and environmental health programs through a variety of other activities. He held an appointment as a visiting professor at Howard University College of Medicine from 1952 to 1976; he has participated actively in the American Public Health Association (president, 1974), the Group Health Association of America (president, 1966-1968), and other professional medical care organizations. Since 1970 he has served on the Advisory Council to the Secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare on Coal Mine Health Research and has appeared frequently before Congressional committees as an advocate and expert witness on occupational and environmental health issues.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and one addition: I. United Mine Workers of America, 1948-1978. II. Other Professional Activities, 1944-1978. III. Writings, 1943-1978. IV. Personal Papers, 1962-1978.
Coal miners and mining; Environmental health; Industrial safety -- Law and legislation; Working class -- Medical care; Labor unions and public health; Lungs -- Dust diseases; Medicaid -- Washington (D.C.); Medical care; Medicine; Occupational diseases; Old age pensions; Public health; Retirement income; Labor unions -- Health facilities; Health-officers; Physicians; Labor movement -- Medical care; Labor -- Medical care; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Kerr, Lorin E., 1909-; District of Columbia. Health Department; United States. Department of Health and Human Services; American Labor Health Association; American Public Health Association; Group Health Association of America; Group Health Institute; Howard University; National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health; National Institute on Rehabilitation and Health Services; Public Health Association (Washington, D.C.); United Mine Workers of America; United States. Department of Labor
- United Mine Workers of America, 1948-1978; Series I; 9 linear feet (22 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  UNITED MINE WORKERS OF AMERICA is organized in two sections: Correspondence and Subject Files and Welfare and Retirement Fund. The bulk of the first section is arranged alphabetically; Interoffice Correspondence is at the end of the section and is arranged chronologically. The second section is organized in subsections which are arranged chronologically. Files designated with an asterisk contain ten or more items.
  Folders with asterisks(*) contain ten or more items.
  - Correspondence and Subject Files
    - A-An (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ap - Ax (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Abrams, Herbert K.(*), 1969-1973, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      General note
      See also: box 11, folder 185 See also: box 11, folder 190 See also: boxes 36-37, folders 202-224 See also: box 38, folder 230 See also: box 42, folder 276
    - Air Line Pilots Association, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aitken, Charles, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - American Academy of General Practice, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Cancer Society, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American College of Chest Physicians, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American College of Radiology(*), 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1966, 1969, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations, Labor Studies Center, Inc., 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - American Health Profiles, Inc., 1970-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - American Industrial Hygiene Association(*), 1969-1970, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - American Lung Association, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - American Medical Association(*), 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - American Rehabilitation Foundation(*), 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - American Thoracic Society, 1966-1967, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Anderson, Robert J.
      See: box 1, folder 15
    - Appalachian Laboratory for Occupational Respiratory Diseases(*), 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Appalachian Pulmonary Laboratory, Inc., 1973, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Appalachian Regional Hospitals, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    - Arnett, Thomas, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Arno Press Inc., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Arons, Milton
      See: box 11, folder 183
    - Association of American Physicians and Surgeons, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Axelrod, Sidney J., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Ba - Bi (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Bl - Bu (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Bank, Richard(*), 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Baumgartner, Leona, 1967, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Beall, J. Glenn, Jr., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Bernstein, Meyer, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Bilsom International, Inc., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Bird, Bedford W., 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      See also: box 11, folder 189 See also: box 12, folder 192
    - Black Lung Association, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Black Lung Educational Fund of West Virginia, 1970, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Blacksville (West Virginia) mine disaster, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Boyle, William A. (Tony)(*), 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      See also: box 7, folder 114 See also: box 11, folders 183-194
    - Brand, Morris, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      See also: box 11, folder 183 See also: boxes 36-37, folders 202-224 See also: box 38, folder 227 See also: box 41, folder 265 See also: box 42, folder 276
    - Brennan, Joseph
      See also: box 11, folder 183 See also: box 12, folder 192 See also: box 12, folder 196
    - Breslow, Lester, 1969, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Brewster, Agnes, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      See also: box 37, folder 217
    - Brindle, James
      See also: box 38, folders 236-237
    - British National Health Service, 1949-1952, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - British Occupational Hygiene Society, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Buffalo Creek (West Virginia) mine disaster, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Byrd, Robert C., 1972, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Ca (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Ce - Com (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Con - Cy (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Ca Detection Laboratories, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Cabin Creek Health Association, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Cander, Leon, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Carroll, Terence E.
      See also: box 3, folder 39 See also: boxes 45-46, folders 307-340
    - Church, Sam, Jr.
      See also: box 12, folder 202
    - Cincinnati, University of, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Civil Rights Act of 1964, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Clayman, Jacob, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Cohen, Wilbur J.
      See also: box 8, folder 147 See also: box 41, folder 263
    - Committee for Health in the 1980 Elections, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Committee for National Health Insurance, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Committee of Physicians for the Improvement of Medical Care, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Comprehensive Health Planning Council of Southeastern Michigan(*), 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Conrad, Ira, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Consumer Protection and Environmental Health Service
      See also: box 4, folder 76
    - Cornelius Printing Company, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Cornell University Conference on Job Stress, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Cornely, Paul B.
      See also: box 11, folder 185
    - Council of the Southern Mountains, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - D (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Davis Memorial Hospital
      See also: box 3, folder 40
    - Davis, Michael M.
      See also: box 41, folder 266
    - Dearing, W. Palmer
      See also: boxes 38-39, folders 226-240 See also: box 41, folders 262-267 See also: box 42, folders 276-278 See also: box 44, folder 294
    - Dellums, Ronald V., 1974, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - District of Columbia, City Council Health and Welfare Council, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - District of Columbia, Department of Vocational Rehabilitation, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Doyle, Henry N., 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Draper, Warren F., 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      See also: box 11, folder 183 See also: box 37, folder 212
    - E (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Environmental Health Programs, Inc., 1970, 1971 January-Dec, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 47-51)
    - Esselstyn, Caldwell B., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      See also: box 15, folder 217 See also: box 17, folders 225, 227 See also: box 41, folders 262-267
    - Esselstyn (Caldwell B.) Foundation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Esselstyn, Willard A.
    - Fa - Fo (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Fr (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Falk, Isidore S.
      See also: box 29, folder 72
    - Falk, Leslie(*), 1966-1978 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Farmington (West Virginia) mine disaster, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Federal Trial Examiners' Conference, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Flood, Daniel, 1973, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Focus, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Ford Foundation, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Foundation for the Handicapped and Elderly, Inc., 1971 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Ga - Go (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Gr - Gu (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Glasser, Melvin, 1965, 1967, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Golden, Benjamin I.(*), 1965, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Goldmann, Franz, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Goldsmith, Frank, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Graves, Jayn, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 62)
      See also: box 11, folder 180
    - Greenburg, Leonard, 1965, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Group Health Association, Inc., 1968, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Guidotti, Frank P.
      See also: box 37, folder 210 See also: box 15, folder 217
    - Ha (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - He - Hi (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Ho - Hy (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Hanover Publications, Inc., 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Hardy, Harriet L.(*), 1968-1978 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      See also: box 11, folder 185 See also: box 11, folder 190
    - Harlan County Legal Defense Fund, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Hazleton Laboratories, Inc., 1970 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Health Research Group, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Hensley, Hubert L., 1969 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Hickel, Walter J., 1970 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Ho11oman, John L. S., 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Human Acoustics, Inc., 1970 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Humphries, Robert, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Hunter, Murray B., 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 71)
      See also: box 11, folder 185 box 11, folder 190
    - Hussey, Hugh H.
      See also: box 1, folder 13
    - I (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Industrial Medical Association(*), 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - International Labor Organization, 1973, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, 1960, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - J (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Johnson, Charles C.(*), 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Joselow, Morris M., 1973, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Journal of Occupational Medicine, 1970-1971, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - K (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Kaiser Foundation Health Plan, Inc., 1968 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Kennedy, Edward M., 1973 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Kentucky Black Lung Association(*), 1969-1973 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Kessler, Henry H.
      See also: box 5, folder 81
    - Kessler Institute for Rehabilitation, 1966, 1971, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Key, Marcus M., 1974 (Box 5, Folder 81)
      See also: box 9, folder 160
    - La - Lin (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Lip - Lu (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Labor's Non-Partisan League, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Legislation
      See also: box 5, folder 84 See also: box 47, folder 28 See also: box 48, folder 41 See also: box 49, folder 64 See also: box 49, folder 68 See also: box 49, folder 75
      - Bills, summaries and testimonies re: occupational health and safety legislation, 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 85)
      - Correspondence and related material re: "Comprehensive Health Planning and Public Health Service Amendments of 1966", 1967 (Box 5, Folder 86)
      - Outline re: A.F.L.-C.I.O. specifications for National Health Insurance, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 87)
      - Bills, summaries and testimonies re: occupational health and safety legislation, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 88)
      - Statement re: H. R. 15390 (R. Nixon), 1972 July 12 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Lewis (John L.) Union Hall, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Lieben, Jan, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Ludwig, Thomas D., 1968-1973 (Box 5, Folder 91)
      See also: box 12, folders 200-201
    - Mac - Map (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Mar - Maz (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Me - Mi (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Moe - Mok (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Mor - My (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - McAteer, J. Davitt, 1973-1974, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - McBeath, William H.
      See also: boxes 23-25, folders 4-36
    - McCarthy, Justin
      See also: box 11, folder 184
    - Magnuson, Warren G., 1973, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - Mayers, Harold J.
      See also: box 11, folder 183 See also: box 36, folder 205 See also: box 36, folder 207 See also: box 41, folder 263
    - Medi-Comp, Inc., 1969 (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - Medical Committee for Human Rights, 1966-1974 (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - Medical Research Council, Pneumoconiosis Research Unit, 1969-1972 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - Melamed, Isidor, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 100)